零一七至零一八嘅財政預算，好嘛？
好高興今日出席財經事務委員會嘅會議，向各位簡介證監會二零一七一八年度嘅預算案。
二零一六一七財政年度預測赤字係五點零七億元，較預算赤字三點九八億元多出咗一點零九億元。
主要嘅原因係徵費收收入較預期少。我哋喺制定預算案時，假設證券市場嘅平均每日成交額為八百七十億元。
證監會制定預算案嘅時候，係着眼於長遠可持續性，等證監會能夠有效咁達至法定目標同落實重點工作。
除非未來證券市場成交額、交易時水平大幅增加，否則證監會預計繼二零一六一七財政年度後會繼續錄得赤字。
首先，我會介紹預算案入邊幾項主要嘅內容，跟住我會解釋證監會喺資源分配方面嘅基本理念，同埋講一講現時影響到本港證券市場質素嘅一啲問題。
聽唔聽唔到撳？啊，係咪我講先定啊？係誒，主席各位財經事務委員會嘅會員誒，大家好誒。首先我同各位拜年，祝大家新年快樂，身體健康，萬事如意。
建議。
但喺預測就調低至七百一十億元。
證券市場成交額係主導證監會收入水平其中一個關鍵因素。
假設每日成交額為八百一十億元，我哋預計二零一七一八年度嘅餘數赤字會係五點三四億元。
鑑於市場成交額往往難以預測，而且波動不定，難免會為我哋喺編制年度預算時增添不確定性。
截至二零一六一七財政年度尾，證監會嘅儲備係六十七點七億元，當中三十億元已撥作為將來購置物業嘅限定用途。
基於預算赤字為五點三四億元計算，會管嘅儲備喺截至二零一七一八財政年度結束嘅時候，將降至六十二點三六億元，因為年度支出三點兩倍。
我哋明白審慎管理財儲備係好重要，我哋以達至長遠財政可持續性為目標。有建院提出，每碗應該購置辦公室物業，作好財政準備。我哋經過詳細考慮，已經採納咗呢個關。
並好似我剛才提到，已預留三十億元撥作限定用途，喺適當時機購買物業作為我哋嘅辦公室。
我想強調一點：，如果之前冇多次調低徵費率，令徵費率近乎減半，政監會係應該能夠達至收支平衡。
顯然赤字預算長遠嚟講並非可持續嘅安排，所以將來我哋唔排除可能要重新評估徵費率嘅水平。
跟住，我會介紹一下證監會嘅工作重點。證監會嘅一個主要目標係推進香港作為國際金融中心嘅穩健發展。
二零一六一七同二零一七八兩個年度連續出現預算赤字，令到政監會喺儲備進一步縮減。預計我哋嘅儲備將會喺未來四至五年減少住，大約相當於年度支出嘅兩倍。
就二零一二年四月起實施嘅牌照年費豁免同調低交易徵費率，我哋就呢兩項措施嘅影響進行過評估。豁免牌照年費喺某程度上有助舒緩持牌中介人，尤其係規模較細嘅公司。
嘅財政負擔呢項措施令證監會每年收入少咗一點九億元嘅排費收入。不過徵費率對證監會收入所帶嚟嘅影響就巨大好多。鑑於證監會喺大約十年前累積咗龐大嘅儲備，我哋曾經三度調低。
就與歐洲市場嘅投眾投資大眾。
我哋喺國際決策過程中扮演積極個角角色，角色。
正如國際貨幣基金組織近期發表嘅報告中，亦有提及。
我哋依家正係同歐洲其他主要市場進行商討，進一步拓展呢項嘅互認安排。
確保我哋就全球化金融市場制定監管工作嘅議題時候，香港同亞洲嘅意見都會好清楚咁畀人聽到。
我哋喺國際監管事務中發揮影響，特別係自從我哋嘅行政總裁歐達禮先生獲選為國際證監會組織理事會主席後，大大咁提升咗香港作為領先全球標準制定者嘅聲譽。
徵費率，另外市場成交額近年一直偏低，按現時嘅百分點零零二七嘅徵費率，除成交額較現時水平大幅增加，否則證監會將會繼續錄得預算赤字，並需要動用儲備嚟應付運作需要。
證監會近年推動幾項重要舉措，鞏固咗香港連接全球同埋內地市場嘅關鍵角色。滬港通開通兩年以來一直運作暢順，基金互認安排喺二零一五年進入咗一個新紀元。香港證監會同。
同中國證監會經過深入磋商，推出咗內地與香港基金互認安排。我哋不久前將基金互認安排拓展至瑞士，呢項舉措開創先河，畀土生土長嘅香港基金首次能夠接直接銷售。
往績係有目共睹。
作更加詳細嘅講解。
我哋收到大量嘅意見書，當中所表達嘅意見紛雲。
業板新上市股份進行配售嘅時候，應達到嘅抽手標準。
最後，我想同大家講下證監會同香港交易所喺上市監管架構進行嘅聯合諮詢。
對投資者保障嘅重視，係我哋將香港發展成為國際金融中心呢個使命好關鍵嘅一部分。
近期新上市創業板股份嘅股價極端波動，只係影響上市市場不同嘅問題入面其中一個例子。
因為要喺全球競爭越趨激烈嘅環境下蓬勃發展，就需要令散户同埋國際機構投資者對我哋穩健嘅監管制度抱有信心。
呢個係好重要同複雜嘅課題，我哋好高興見到公眾熱切關注市場監管，因為呢個課題對香港作為國際金融中心嘅整體定位嚟講係最重要嘅。
投資者保障係證監會工作嘅重心，無論係透過監察中介機構、打擊申當行為嘅執法行動，同埋我哋目前對上市市場質素嘅關注，我哋都係以公眾利益為依歸。
嘅資源喺呢個過程裡面，我哋會作出審慎嘅假設，採取嚴格嘅財務監控，同埋揾出可調配現有資源嘅範疇。證監會嘅儲備水平多或少都唔會影響呢個決定嘅。
正係對創業板嘅運作進行檢討。另外，我哋都同香港交易所喺其他監管事情合作，着手處理更加廣泛嘅市場質素問題，去出眾市場發展嘅目標，又同時能夠保障大眾嘅利益。
毫無疑問，本地同國際傳媒就呢個現象嘅報導同輿論，加上涉及主板同創業板公司嘅失當行為個案，確實已經令市場嘅升與受損。而我哋亦採取咗行動，最近證監會發表咗一份指引，説明中介人為錯。
雖然我哋發出咗指引嘅同時，亦聯同香港交易所就配售發表咗聲明，不過噉樣依然係唔足夠嘅，毫無疑問，我哋有必要要做更多嘅工作，令投資者對本港嘅上市市場重拾信心。證監會同香港交易所依家。
多謝大家。
已經開始運作。
多謝主席。
誒，第一個陳振英議員。
各位就證監會嘅報告有咩嘢發問嘅？請舉手。
將會分佈喺六個唔同嘅部門嚟支援更加複雜同大量嘅執法同法律行動。
及應付因為持牌法法團進行受規管活動嘅持續增加，同數量龐大嘅持牌人而產生嘅工作。
本年度我哋同樣建議只略為調整人手，調整幅度為百分之三，同二零一六一七年嘅水平差唔多。我唔開設咗二十八個新職位。
最後，而同樣重要嘅，我哋建議喺二零一七一八年度維持現行嘅百分點零零二七嘅徵費率，同埋繼續寬免牌年寬免牌照年費。
無論係支持定反對有關建議，當中好多件書都極具建設性，對我哋喺探討未來最佳嘅路向非常有幫助。當然，我哋需要仔細仔細分析所收到嘅意見，並且會喺未來嘅一次會議上向委員會。
講翻我哋嘅預算案，我向各位委員保證，我哋奉行非常嚴謹嘅財理財方針嚟決定預算支出。首先，我哋會問：如果達成本年度所定定嘅監管重點同埋履行法定目標，證監會需要咩？
我哋喺二零一零年至到二零一五年間，因情況需要而測聘大量人手。雖然係噉，正如我哋舊年所講，我哋認為證監會依家嘅規模大致上差唔多，所以人手增幅相對比較少。我哋亦都已經着手對證監會嘅運作。
進行咗策略性嘅檢討，而且藉助科技，等我哋喺無需增加人事開支嘅情況下提升工作效率。舉個例，我哋嘅法規執行部以以專責團隊同清清清晰工作為重點嘅全新組織架構。
我希望剛才簡介能夠畀各位委員清楚瞭解我哋管理同分配財政資源嘅理念，務求令證監會繼續收做到一個成效同埋效率兼具嘅監管機構。歐特禮先生同我本人都好樂意解答各位委員嘅問題。
誒唔該，主席好簡單嘅誒幾個問題啫。第一個咧就係誒睇到證監會個年度調薪咧，就係四點五個percent，噉啊高於誒通脹率嘅噉，想請問誒係咪有咩背後嘅特殊原因啦？第二咧就係資訊及系統服務費咧，就誒雖然增加咗三十三個percent，但係。
銀碼其實得一千八百萬到嘅啫，咁誒，因為證監會都係一個好重要嘅監管機構啦。咁最近啲網絡安保嗰啲問題係好嚴重嘅，譬如怕人哋嚟攻擊。咁其實誒呢個費用係咪已經包咗你哋要提升網絡安保方面誒嘅費用咧？因為我見到下邊誒學習發展費用得。
which are are to do with
Actually， under second I T question.
the basically hijacking share trading accounts.
Because obviously, there's a spending implication for the industry on that.
In a way that is efficient, and that's really about that's how we that's the the rationale for the for the systems change and the spend on that. Just on cybersecurity. Just secondly, clearly the other issue which we are dealing with, as is the HKMA, is cybersecurity in the industry.
我諗就未必需要財政司長特別去審核，因為即係證監都係個獨立機構，嘅財政都係自己係去做。我哋喺呢個預算已經係提出咗，我哋有呢個可能性。我諗呢個係即係通告咗誒誒呢個可能性嘅，係多多謝議員。
七十六萬噉，呢個係第二個大問題。第三個問題咧就係誒，其實我知道今日證監會嘅預算咧，就誒，其實我哋唔係一個審批嘅角色，類似備識嘅角色啦。咁如果一旦證監會決定想自己購置物業咧，咁購置物業嗰個決定嗰陣時咧，誒，到時立法會嗰個角色係咪都係一個備識？
角色定係話一個真係要到時係審批嘅角色咧？咁呢三個簡單問題，唔該。誒，主席。誒，多謝議員。或者我解答第一個同埋第二個問題，就交畀歐達禮先生解答第二個問題。第一個問題咧，我哋每年係誒做我哋嘅財政預算案時咧，都邀請。
外邊嘅專家去做個問卷嚟翻嚟報告咧，佢哋估計喺財政喺財務方面、金融方面嘅明年嘅加幅度係會點樣嘅？咁得翻嚟結果咧就係百分之四至四點五左右。噉我哋而家要預算四點百分之。
四點五咧係個預算嚟嘅啫，唔表示到係真係到做人工決定嗰陣時咧係會呢個數嘅。即係我哋有個過程，我哋嗰個所謂誒reimbursement committee會再開會去檢討而家嘅市場嘅情況，先再決定呢個四點五係個預算嗰個數啊誒。當
多謝誒議員。第三個問題咧就係誒我哋依個誒預算案咧喺誒財經事務委員會交代咗之後咧，最後要係要財政司司長去十去去確定嘅。咁變咗你講好啱，即係我哋如果將來係國
真係去買物業揾到適合嘅物業咧，誒，我哋都有呢個過程。誒，係要嚟翻誒到加我哋預算案嗰時，誒會係做呢個誒誒誒介紹啦，同埋最後個預算案都要係財政司司長去審批。但你話真正係買唔買咧？
Yeah, just to pick up on that last question about buying office premises, I think it would be inevitable that it would be discussed in Legco in the context of the of the budget, because it would be such a big budgeting decision for the SFC at that time. But we'll be starting to assess options for buying office.
premises next year, because our next break lease break comes around in 2020. So that's the opportunity to to make a move on the question of IT. I mean, you're absolutely right. It is incredibly it is an incredibly important area, and we have got an
my first question is.
好，下一位誒副主席。
會被增加至945。
and litigation cases, you need more lawyers.
兩個問題。一，我我。
SFC was under-resourced for the job it had to do, and we did increase the headcount quite substantially until a couple of years ago.
by by year 2030. I I I I can't foresee how how how your operation.
Would you be willing to give us a kind of guarantee that I mean your had kang would not be expanding, you know, you know, incessantly because
會 be like, but I I'm I'm I'm quite you know concerned that your headcount would go on expanding without any cap. That is my first question. And and secondly,
I'm just wondering whether it would be more cost-effective if some of your legal services can be outsourced rather than having your in-house legal team being expanded.
Increased expenditure on that, the expenditure actually isn't about. Interestingly, is not about hardware that tended to be the IT spend in previous years for many organisations. This is all about systems, and because it's about systems, a large component of that does relate to the security of those systems.
And associated with that is a kind of legacy issue, which again many organisations face, which is that old IT infrastructure tends to be quite siloed, so it's very difficult for the organisation to manage the totality of information it has.
Because if you, if you, as I do sitting now as chairman of IOSCO, if you ask regulators in the industry what is the number one threat, not surprisingly it's all about cyber attacks, and we've seen that happen not only in banking but also in brokers in in Hong Kong, and in particular recent attacks.
So, just very briefly, we have just completed a series of workshops with the industry, and what we want to do is then establish a cybersecurity baseline in our code of conduct to make sure that the all in the industry are clear what those standards are, and in particular, there's level playing.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I read from the paper regarding the increase in the head count. Altogether, the total number of head count of SFC for the year two thousand and seventeen eighteen.
In fact, quite concerned about the the expansion of had康，because year on year, I mean, you probably will will will have you know new reason or justification for increasing had康。Now it's 945, it's approaching a thousand, and in particular, I can。
see that among the new positions you have described in your paper, eight of those you know positions relate to the legal services department, and of course you've given me as the reason that because of the complication and and seriousness of of investigation case.
嗯。
believe that it continues to make sense.
Now, in relation to the cost effectiveness.
reason why there is an eight-person increase, which is largely devoted to litigation cases in in LSD.
A couple of years ago, we then made the judgement that we had reached just about the right size for the organisation.
嗯，can， in relation to， LSD thus legal services and enforcement etc.
And you'll see this year, that is the effectively the cap that we've imposed this year, this time round for the for the seventeen eighteen budget.
Now and again, I don't think there's any reason to suppose that in the following year we wouldn't continue to impose discipline of sort of three percent.
In the past, actually quite a long time ago, the the legal services did brief out to local law firms as well as council. Now, it's tradition is to brief out to council only directly.
So, my expectation going forward, just to answer the last question about, or the first question about not increasing expansion, I would say that if you know graphically we did increase, and now we're plateauing, and I think my expectation that that plateauing will continue.
我有個 feeling， that perhaps I mean the SFC's legal services department will be the size of a a medium-sized law firm already. So, can can you just you know brief me on that, please? Thank you.誒，我請阿歐達禮先生回答誒副主席嘅問題。Okay. Yeah. Okay. Well, look, on the headcounters is a
Obviously, a major issue for us, and it and it does. It is a an issue of concern because certainly, you know, for the public as a whole. And there are many comments about headcount. Now, I think the reality is that some years ago, four or five years ago, there was no doubt in our mind at board level in the SSC that the
You know, obviously subject to the caveat, if there are further challenges or further jobs, the remit expands, etc. We would need to increase. So at that point, there was a decision that we would limit headcount increases to no more than three per year.
你 may have noticed that enforcement actually hasn't requested any further headcount increase this year. That is simply because we recognised that many of the bottlenecks in processing enforcement cases actually sat in legal services rather than the enforcement division itself, and that's the principal.
and that's simply because we found that that was in reality more efficient and cheaper. We did not pay outside law firm fees, and on top of that, we didn't have to educate the outside law firms as to the sort of intricacies of the cases we dealt with. So on those two counts, it made it made sense. and
可以，哦，主席，你gentleman，just one follow question. I mean, in in the economic climate where our GDP growth is less than three percent, I'm quite surprised to learn that your annual growth rate will be capped at three percent. I would urge the board of SFC to critically review the cap because I I find
我覺得 quite you know excessive the three percent increase in the kind of cap you you you're putting. Can you promise that you will review this you know kind of upper limit growth as soon as possible? 嗯，多多謝副主席，我哋個個誒董事會一定會誒。
誒誒，研究你頭先提嘅建議，不過想講咧，好多時咧，誒個GDP growth係低，同埋或者個經濟環境唔好咧，反而犯罪嘅人就多嘅。咁變咗咧，個環境越唔好咧，調翻轉頭咧，可能仲要監管係仲要嚴緊咗，因為啲人揾唔到錢。
即誒。
自己係一位石蟹鄉委員。
SFC喺依一方面咧，係有一定嘅誒活動性喺度，而係可以畀佢令到依個增長嘅時間係可以去去做嘅。依個第一點。
主席，your your your argument is that in a boom time or in a recession time you will need more manpower. Okay, never mind. But please just I would like the board to review this, you know, growth limit.一定一定，好似係。
就第二點咧，我好希望咧，SFC即係經過依個S誒，我我都係喺二千年嗰陣時坐喺度，用咗四年咧，睇依個SFC嗰個Ordinance嗰度咧，係都係寫得好清楚，係畀到你哋有依個權。
人去用，但係SFC本身自己一個獨立機構喺度咧，我希望咧，因為我都個人都覺得應該要畀翻依個依個所謂活動性嘅誒，畀SFC而係佢哋有效管治嘅，我覺得依個係好。所以你又叫SFC嗰個誒？
咧誒就會諗有冇走後門啊，所以即係話我依兩個咧就唔係誒一個direct relationship。不過我我明白你意思，我哋個個個董事會有有噉嘅責任係make sure我哋唔係誒白費公堂啊嘛，係咪？我我我接受你嘅意見。So so，what what I can gather from from Mr.
主席，就我係支持SFC今次攞上嚟嘅budget嘅。喺人手嗰邊咧，一個我就有少少唔同嘅睇法，因為我哋唔可以啊，因為一個係依個誒喺SFC嘅性質裏邊咧，尤其是喺香港做一個金融公誒中。
一路咁去發展喺度，我哋要配要令到啲人才要喺度，唔係聽到有噉嘅需求嗰陣時先請人咧。嗰陣時未必可以配合到F S S F C嗰個增長同埋嗰個監察個個工作喺度，所以即係喺人手嗰度咧，我哋都要相信咧。
由依個誒誒責任去去去去做，我唔記得咗依係set車咪under誒依個依個director board嘅investigation啊。誒係應該係哦，咁咁咧就噉你哋去做咧，是有又可以有check and balance喺度咧，所以我覺得係依個。
係你喺你個角度睇，或者有噉嘅權。
決定去去執行，點解咧？我哋而家轉政府啦。
攞翻嚟畀阿主席，我哋依個F.A.Panel。
而家你就係包公嚟㗎啦！你去，你去，你有條法例喺度，你去執法，你查，你去做，你決定曬。
主席唔好意思，我繼續少少冇人喺度。因為如果你係諮詢出個諮詢報告嗰陣時咧，唔該你翻返未做任何嘅國未做任何嘅決定。
你唔參與之中，當佢係使權嗰陣時過火咗㗎啦，依個好大問題。所以我好希望咧，我唔見到，唔想見到好似美國阿Trump噉，出啲Executive Order。
可以用日可以畀到睇到SFC去去點去加人手啊？喺邊方面加人手咧？你如果你用一個cap去誒誒man power cap去控制住咧，依個或者對各部門有啲影響，同時政依個唔係一個政府嘅機構喺度，因為政府個機構可以通道咁去調人過去借住。
個council去自己去檢討應該嘅，但係我覺得久唔久咧，SFC都應該要請一請director audit嚟睇一睇，就係幫你做個所以話誒value for money audit嚇，行工量值角度去睇，即係你咁去咧，就畀到你哋一個誒營收性仲更加大。
係嚇，喺度即係每一個你做得好唔怕去咁做，所以我係支持呢個budget。另外，我想咧，即係你哋當你哋係有一個誒，係個諮詢文件頭先主席你提出嚟咧，我唔希望咧見到咧，因為你哋又係當我好鼓勵你哋去做增，你喺。
呢個做你嘅工作做得好嗰陣時咧，唔係應該要加大你嘅工作喺度。你嘅工作你睇睇翻你SFC ordinance寫得好清楚，忽然間咧你由呢個SFC變溝埋去個呢個stock exchange嗰度咧，有一個好大問題。所以你嘅諮詢嗰度，我唔知你嘅諮詢嗰度點去。
但係你未諮詢之前咧，你你未去出個諮詢文件嗰陣時咧，你已經都冇嚟呢個F A panel，即係我哋呢個粉領組講畀我哋聽，你個你個個方向係點做？你有冇即係好多人咧，或者係啱與錯咧，覺得你超越咗out virus。
去你依個F.S.SecurityFinanceAudience嗰度咧，因為是我哋唔係好多個正喺度，真真係少個。我我係其中一個可以講得最後嗰幾個喺度㗎啦。噉啊，我就好清晰就去睇下每一樣嘢，我哋監察你哋，唔係監察定你使錢，係監察你用權。
有冇過過過過火咗？用權係咪已經啱咗？你哋有冇去到令到你哋嘅個責任喺個SFO嗰度咧？係行政府應該要看得好實，但係我哋呢個政府有時咧真係瞓覺嘅，對唔住啊嚇！即係嚇就就係冇唔幹。
嚇！你你嗰個權大到你可以用好多executive order，好似阿Trump噉，但係係咪對香港好嘅咧？對香港市場發展係咪好嘅咧？即係呢樣嘢，你係好清晰地。有時主席，我唔係教你，即係我知我我對你一百個percent信心，但係即係希望即係唔好畀啲佢哋Parkinson's Law一。
一路加大去，一路加權，一路咁去做咧，對香港整體個等到我哋應該要做嘅工作做得唔好，而家收花都係好好，唔好因為要加要要要要要幫救咗棵樹嚟失去咗個個樹林喺度，所以咧我希望咧，如果你
去睇依個係我哋應該要監察住你哋嘅工作，所以錢嗰方面我唔覺得係需要問題，但係你個權行使個權咧，立法嗰陣時喺依個法法例係我哋立出嚟，我哋有個責任要保護香港金融穩定，香港嘅法例係配合到你個。
發展多謝主席嚇。主席有乜回應？係係多多多謝阿石議員誒。我諗講嗰個諮詢嗰度咧，即係誒多謝你嘅意見誒。我哋收咗好多誒嗰個誒文件誒回應咧，亦都有誒包唔咗頭先你講嗰啲。
其實。
public， as such。
語，但係唔參與。
The institutions that
急住去，去要有限時間限制係。
嗯，所以，yeah。Thank you, Chairman. If I may reply to Mr. Ashley, while appreciating all the goodwill that you have, but putting in a consultation papers to the
Around this, that is just not tenable at all. And we've we've looked at submissions that raise issues about ultraviruses, intraviruses, etc. And of course, they will be taken into account along with all the other submissions that have come in across the spectrum.
誒意見嘅，即係我哋係保持開放態度，係會去分析所有嘅意見。誒當然我哋絕對係聽到你講，誒我哋唔會去濫用你嘅權，呢個係當然好重要啦。噉我哋會係好似頭先講係係誒聽曬所有意見，而去慢慢分析。誒到最後係做一個係對。
香港市場有益有利嘅最後嘅方案。誒，我亦都知道啊。誒，陳家強局長已經係同個誒誒誒財誒財政事務委員會咧，係提及到或者四月會嚟誒同個委員會彙報。我諗到時係佢會有。
有畀你哋再新嘅誒誒誒update㗎。我哋四月份有個議程去討論嘅，係係議程。係我我想跟進可唔可以啊？阿石太醫，我哋有時間。好，我想咧，即係我好希望咧，我唔見到，我好唔想見到一個咁急促嘅你哋嘅決。
嚇！三月廿六號我哋要選啦。七月一號有新政府，邊個做財政司？邊個做呢個新嘅官員？或者佢有新嘅諗法？你哋話係做任何對市場好嘅，你哋去做。但係喺個法律嘅各框架裏邊咧，我注重嘅法律框架裏邊係要影響到，因為。
因為你個權都好闊㗎，但係你有冇幹預到short exchange嗰個行使？有冇幹預到short exchange嗰個嗰個權咧？因為唔係要上壓，但係你哋兩互相監督喺度，你有你嘅性質，佢有佢嘅性質喺度，所以你唔可以話你你做包工，你乜嘢都去。
依個係我哋賦予畀你嗰陣時，而而嗰個S.F.O.，但係唔係畀你濫用去用，因為唔係話你濫用。我當你行使嗰陣時，同埋我希望，我好希望咧，我係會反對任何七月一號之前執行呢樣嘢。你知道，你知道啊，主席，我係係係。
反對聲音一份子嚟，但係我我係好開放地去聽你哋去點講依個，所以依個影響到金融中心一個係一個好大好大。依個我哋唔可以行差一步。今時今日都係唔錯嘅香港，但係如果你哋係要去要令到佢更加好。
唔係一個問題，但係要做到唔好影響到今時今日嗰個行，即係依個依個我哋現有嘅制度喺度嚇。多謝曬主席，係誒誒，多多謝議員我我或者畀阿阿我哋嘅C.E.O.再再補充下。我想講，我多謝你嘅寶貴意見，我亦都冇個時間表，唔係話。
Yeah, I mean, look, it is. I mean, as I think, as the chairman said, it's the consultation has given rise to lots and lots of discussion and many many submissions, which I our view is a good thing because it it recognises that the topic that was raised is important, and it it fundamentally is about.
About the quality of the of the listing market. The second thing I'd say is that the the proposals in the joint consultation was a model that was agreed to exposed agreed between ourselves and the exchange leadership to be exposed to the public. But we have an open mind as to where
We land ultimately on this. I mean, from our perspective, you know, the overarching goal, given that we are encountering some quality problems—if I can call them those—in the listed market, the overarching goal is to have a regulatory system as between ourselves and the.
exchange that is is transparent, that is efficient, more efficient than it is now, and is also publicly accountable. And transparency and public accountability go together. How we end up achieving that is is is another matter potentially, but clearly the
嘅。
好，第二次發言啊，副主席。
This is not the way that the financial market should operate. This is not the way that Hong Kong should be governed.
market a Hong Kong market to be the predominant IPO market worldwide. We want Hong Kong to stay in number one.
你知，呢，呢係為咗整個事情，呢，我們需要進步，而進步需要不斷的審核，但係誰會審核SFC？
company itself, of course, it get the dual function. It it also acts as a regulator. Of course, I mean its power is sort of
I'm so glad that the chairman bring this sub subject up. I don't actually want to raise this issue in this new year goodwill goodwill period, you know.
unless you find that there's something wrong, if there's something wrong, why now you put in a consultation? You should fix it immediately. I'm not teaching you, but I'm voicing out as a participant in the game.
for many many more years, so we need to be, you know, seen to be complying with the best standard. Now, of course, there are many forms of regulatory models worldwide. In some of the jurisdictions, the stock exchange don't even have a.
and I that's why I said that that Hong Kong is now very transparent. While you have all you with all your good intention, it might not be good for the market. That the market has been working out well. You can improve it. If there's nothing wrong with the system, why fix it?
Proposals generated the discussion. The third thing I say is that absolutely right. I mean, there is there should be no possibility of the SFC stepping outside its statutory powers around any kind of final recommendations or structure.
The government or whichever bodies put up this consultation document should not take a stance. And I have blasted the secretary for treasury that he have took a stand of of deciding which is best for Hong Kong. When it when you do a consultation
啊啊！所謂啊，put up the consultation idea， should let the the market should let the public to decide and come back with ideas. But so far the SFC and the government have taken a very unilateral.
stance of pushing it through. This is not Hong Kong. This is not the normal way of doing consultation. Consultation means consultation. It's not mean a guided democracy that you can do what think whatever you do as long as you do the things that I like. And this.
Nobody. While you were saying that you have you have consulted the stock exchange, how can they not listen to you? Take a view that you they are under your supervision. The whole whole thing is all just a make up of everything. So if you put up a consultation, I urge and I plead that.
free of guidance.
So, think about it.
framework of the system.
Okay，主席，主席refer。
嗰個上市諮詢文件咧。
Pew is being made and all that is quite unclear, and I would.
或者誒，最後我都講講啊嘛，主席。
more detail no model for us to discuss, and I think.
On a more global scale, the direction you are pursuing is correct. Thank you.
Thirdly, that my dear friend, this is their different opinion in this council.
我答問，介時答問，因為佢佢話佢唔同意我講。我我，I appreciate the wisdom of the。
副議長，但係我back to devil，他誤解我，我係 all for the consultation，但係我 want the consultation。
一 kiss of death from an enemy， or kiss of death from your friend， you decide to choose。after all， both you have both sides of your faces to be kissed。
urge the SFC and and the government to to give deeper thought into the various you know comments received so far and develop a
Consultation must be fairly spread to the extent that not to be guided by SFC nor even the government. I have actually blasted the secretary for treasury in one of the council meeting here, and this is my personal opinion. And I
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Well, in fact, I have a quite different view from Mr. Shack, and I think the consultation do give a lot of chances and opportunities for us to voice out your your your stance. In fact, I I think you you have given us quite a
Good time frame to come in on the to kind of regulatory framework. Now, I think to be to be very clear, I think the SFC is subject to the scrutiny of the Legislative Council. That's very clear, and the stock exchange as a listed company.
limited as well in certain circumstances, but overall, of course, I mean we need to balance between a a sustainable growth in the market and also good quality company seeking listing or equity capital in our market, and we want our
一 regulatory role, but we are having a mixed model, and the demarcation of responsibility between the stock exchange and the SFC is quite clear. But of course, I mean there are certain areas we would like to see more clarification in the consultation because of the way how the
In this case, the government and the SFC have been actively pushing something that that these market have yet to really respond. That's one thing. Second thing is that we are always aim to achieve the best in term of standard. That's okay, but you must work within the framework.
增加廿一個。
完全睇唔到有改善。
即係最主要咧，就顧及公眾嘅利益。
烏煙瘴氣，大上大落，操控市場。
反而咧，你哋集中精神注喺嗰啲中介公司度。
所以我哋希望，即係喺嗰個誒市場，即係。
但係你年年增加咁多人手，但係市場嘅嗰個。
中嘅公司最近咧，你哋有條條例合適性都令到我哋咧好大嘅困困。
誒，我討論咗好多，誒，我亦都瞭解咗好多，誒，業界都畀好多意見我嘅。
即係我哋唔可以將嗰個回歸之後，我哋辛辛苦苦建立嘅金融中心，用一小撮人。
我哋覺得無論呢個交易所又好，證金又好，嗰個監管同埋市場嘅發展應該取得平衡。
噉我哋覺得咧，即係喺諮詢文件度係確實有好多地方可以改良嘅，但係我係絕對唔認同咧，可以全部將個諮詢文件撤銷嘅。
嗰個成交量咧，呢度同你過分監管我哋中介人士嗰個嗰個發展我哋本地有我哋本地特色嘅經紀行嘅運作係有關嘅。
霸佔咗整個嘅金融嘅發展嘅嗰個成果，所以我哋覺得咧，即係呢個證金會咧喺嗰個適當嘅監管上面咧啊，應該起咗一個作用，讓我哋社會嘅資源能夠公平啲嘅分配，呢樣資。
能夠咧，即係吸引更多嘅優質嘅企業嚟上市，同埋吸引更多嘅投資者。啊，呢個我係對個諮詢文件嘅睇法。我而家想問嘅就係證監會每年都增加人手，即係今年就增加二十八個，舊年好似我冇記錯就。
困惑，因為我哋就算攞到啲生意有客人，我哋都唔敢點做，唔知點做，唔知會唔會即係我哋嘅表達同呢個誒合適性啊嘅嘅言列有冇嗰個嗰個衝突，所以我哋覺得咧，即係話如果你應該咧增加。
快啲快啲！
噉啊，第二咧就係嗰個。
咁關於個市場質素咧，我完全同意你講法。我哋好關心、好關注最近市場質素嘅問題。我哋亦都開始做做咗好多工作，或者我畀阿阿阿歐大禮先生去解解索。你而家做咗咩嘢？係多謝。
都仍然係嚴峻嘅，仍然係即係誒唔可以嗰個個雙鞋嘅，所以我哋覺得咧，即係未來呢兩年，我哋希望正金即係仲仍然咧可以豁免我哋嗰個排費，只不過係一點九億元嘅啫。
對於嗰個操控市場或者係誒新股上市誒，即係嗰個貨源關邊呢啲咧，應該整頓一下。對於嗰個誒，應該誒，即係努力去發展誒嗰個勤勤力力去去去去誒拓展個市場嘅。
你哋應該多啲誒，即係嗰個支持嘅噉，所以我就希望咧，你哋咧即係喺未來嘅呢兩年咧，嗰個誒排費仍然咧都可以擴展，因為咧未來我哋睇到嗰個經濟狀況啊、國際形勢又好啊。
至於咧嗰個買嗰個寫字樓，我哋都希望咧，即係誒綜合大家嘅意見咧，你係咪可以即係唔需要喺最高貴，即係最最最最誒矜貴嘅地點去買咧？去去到去到咧，即係次一級嘅嗰個嗰個寫字樓去買咧？
一樣可以做到嗰個效果出嚟。金管好咧，唔自在咧，你個地點辦事設設喺邊度？金管好咧，係一個體制嚟嘅，係一個市場咧，即係誒嗰個持續發展嘅一個基礎。所以我哋希望咧，即係既然咧，即係喺嗰個誒環境唔係咁好嘅環境之下咧，後。
考慮寫字樓咧，可以考慮到啊，即係次一級嘅寫字樓啊。咁呢個咧，亦都唔好下下咧就即係一見到有隻字咧，就要喺市場收費，要向我哋咧經紀嗰方面去去去着去諗着數。OK，多多多謝主席。或者喺個諮詢文件度咧，或者。
想只係講一句咧，就話誒好多謝主席、副主席同埋尊敬嘅石議員嘅意見，可以反映到誒今日幾個只有幾個會員都已經有三個唔同嘅意見。噉你可以見到咧，你哋三個都係反映咗我哋收好多個文件咧嘅唔同嘅意見，係反映成個市場嘅。
睇法唔一樣嘅，所以我哋嗰個誒去做嗰個誒審核研究咧，你可以見到係個工作都幾幾大挑戰性。誒，依個對證監會好重要。誒，但我哋所以係要需時間去慢慢分析，然後到最後先決定誒將來嘅方案係點樣。我哋絕對而家係未。
有一個決定，我哋保持好開放嘅態度。咁多多多謝大家。誒噉啊，即係我想講講咧，就係講買購買物業嗰度咧。誒，阿主席，你放心，我哋絕對唔會話以係誒好似冇無底深潭咁買個好貴物業，同埋咧，我哋都亦都絕對會考慮，唔係淨係中環其他嘅地方。
係比較嘅價錢冇咁貴，我亦都會需要考慮，或係咪將個我哋嘅物業分開兩度或者三度地方去去嚟做？因為咧，始終我哋喺中環咧誒都要有個代表性嘅。咁但係其他大部分可以唔喺喺中環外邊，亦都會係受考慮嘅。所以大家放心。
for the industry.
thank you.
market misconduct。
有 adequate provisions。
啊！蛇仔黐尾啊！
of the financial market.
make sure that it is for the greater good of the.
I think what the chairman said that is not three different opinions. The opinion is that we want to improve the market.
I think to the chairman's question about the brokerage community. I mean, clearly they are dependent on the market itself being of sufficient and we use the word quality. But in particular, over you know recent, quite recent years, there's been increasing instances.
of problems and frankly misconduct, both in the gem market but also to an extent in the in the main board market, and that does not is not conducive to investor confidence. And if investor confidence drops, then interest in trading in the market and participating drops, and that is a real issue.
That we were focused on. Now you have to take a multi-pronged approach to this. We are working with the stock exchange on specific issues around JEM. You may have seen that recently we we issued a circular to do with the expectations of placing agents.
When it comes to making gem IPO placings, which is one problem, but it's not the whole story. Part of the story is around the overall positioning of gem itself as a stepping stone to the main board. Others to do with are to do with whether or not there should be a public float element in an offering, and those are those are all questions. They need to be looked at.
So there's a policy component to this. There's also an investigation and enforcement component. Enforcement, in my experience, is always difficult. It always takes longer than you would like, but nevertheless, it's incredibly important to deter. And it's interesting that the proportion of cases we deal with across the piece, whether it's
Whether it's insider dealing, etc., etc., the proportion that is around corporate issues, listed corporate issues, has increased over time, and that's certainly the case right now. So, those efforts, I think, around the quality of the market and conduct in the market.
Are going to be important to the brokerage community. So for our suitability, I think you mentioned the suitability requirement. We issued a circular just before Christmas, which is intended to articulate both when suitability is triggered, the obligation to ensure that an investment product is suitable for your client.
as well as a separate set of FAQs around what to do when it is triggered, and it was now the intention of that was to be both realistic and helpful, and you know one of the advantages we have around the way in which we operate as a principles-based regulator as opposed to
Rules-based, which is more sort of US approach, is that we can continue to work with the industry and refine those FAQs. So, I'm not saying that the suitability requirement itself is necessarily easy to discharge in all circumstances. But to the extent that we're able to give greater guidance around when it's triggered and what to do, that must be, I think, a good thing for the.
and the consultation is a good way of looking at it. But what I'm saying is, I do not disagree with the chairman or the deputy chairman. I'm not asking for the withdrawal of the of the consultation papers. What I'm saying is that if you want to make any decision.
not for the purpose ofSFC, or for the under purpose of the stock exchange, whatever reasons they have. Secondly, the purpose that the points that the chairman made about the market disruption and all this problem facing the market, the SFO.
好啊！
有邊個回應？
阿陳振英第三次發言。
and this is a little bit frightening.
administration of the laws.
Improved that, but within your existing regulation, you can do that.
You do not need new laws. You do not need new powers. The power is all-embracing. It's so wide. The power in the SFO.
係同議員去分享，我哋唔會誒急於咧喺某一個時間咧就匆匆咧攞有關嘅一啲分析同埋嗰個嘅誒意見咧嚟嚟會傾嘅，噉我哋一定會從長計議嘅。多謝主席。
to police all these cases, you do not need new laws to do that. And but what you have done is there are provisions within the SFO that you can do it.
所以我唔見到咩係問題。你允許呢啲噉嘅嘢發生，有規例係要你去管理，令到佢哋可以消除呢啲嘅錯誤。問題係有效嘅。
架構諮詢嘅個目的咧，其實係要提升嗰個市場嗰個效率，同埋精簡個程序嘅。我一定一定會朝呢一個方向，確保咧日後誒嘅嗰個嘅路向咧，係依據嗰個法律嘅框架嚟到做。
and while the chairman said that that you should tighten up, look at look at what happened to the the whole problem of Lehman Brothers, how the banks have actually improved in their governance and others, but for the stock market situation is slightly different. I can see that you try to
誒多謝主席，多謝阿石議員嘅誒意見，同埋剛才幾位議員就住個上市諮詢嘅嗰個嘅誒目前嘅情況同埋個未來路向都表達咗意見。正如頭先，剛才阿阿證監堂主席所講啦，誒政府同埋證監同埋交易所就住呢個上市嘅。
亦都能夠達到有關嘅目的。咁誒，正如頭先我哋都提到咧，誒，我哋會安排當證監會同埋誒交易所就住呢一個嘅諮詢誒嘅收集到嘅意見，做咗一個分析之後咧，一定會拎翻嚟呢一個財經事務委員會咧，作一個長進嘅討論。我哋亦都。
要求先，剛才都聽到啦。誒，我四月咧，其實只係一個初步嘅一個估算。當我哋同秘書處咁一定咧，最緊要就係證監同埋誒交易所咧，能夠就收到咁多大量嘅一啲意見咧，作咗詳盡嘅分析，有啲進度嘅報告咧，我哋先至會喺適當嘅時候咧，搦嚟咧。
誒主席，好簡單嘅頭先講咧，嗰個諮詢文件咧，因為誒就係咁誒controversial啦，所以誒當四月又好或者五月又好拎翻上嚟財經事務委員會討論完之後咧，我希望最尾個方案可能係誒midway between一啲嘢嘅噉，但。
啊。
OK，噉啊。
正正確，唔該唔該，得。
did not envisage having to change any rules. That that's correct.
你就話即係總之傾到大家都覺得嗰個係一個相對比較誒攞到共識嘅方案，噉我哋先去。究竟係七月一號之前咧定之後，我又覺得誒呢個就睇真真正正嘅時間點樣流轉咯。唔該曬主席。
係一位啊副主席，多謝主席，多謝主席。誒，我想即係一個技術委想澄清咧，其實即係我想誒誒證監會或者啊啊啊唐生澄清下咧。
我或者想講講就係誒，議員絕對四月一號誒嚟嗰個會議，到時唔會有一個決定嘅。依個絕對可以同你咁講。誒，其他你嘅頭先嘅提議，我哋會誒考慮你嘅你嘅意見。多謝。
仲有咩意見？如果冇咧，就好多謝正金委主席同埋Ashley咧，誒同我哋讀報告。想唔係我想問，即係我想回應問啊啊啊唐主席㗎，就係佢講講講得咁正確嘅咧，可唔可以畀份文件我哋我哋嘅FA panel？
主席，我叫政府，我我家係交個交個波畀政府。唔該，你交份文件。如果係有需要更改任何嘅嘢，你用executive order去喺邊個SFO嗰個條例，喺邊個stock exchange嗰條條例。
嗯，你哋諮詢文件入邊所提議嘅改革嘅所有嘅嘅程序啊，或者做法咧，係唔會涉及任何法例嘅修改？呢呢樣嘢可唔可以同我澄清下咧？或者各位委員啦，唔該。誒誒，正確。
係去到嗰個點裏邊咧，可能兩邊都仲會有一輪意見。噉啊，頭先阿石議員就話誒，可唔可以睇下新嘅政府班子七月一號之後先至做啦？噉我覺得咧，又誒呢個係其中一個理想嘅時間點啦。但係正如頭先啊，即係誒誒財富局嗰邊都講咧，就冇一個既然既然冇一個特定。
時限嘅話咧，就算上嚟傾完，出咗一個新嘅方案咧，嗰個方案應該再拎出去市場畀大家再做一次嘅嘅一個諮詢，然後先至去定。唔係話哦，我聽咗咁多意見啦，我就定咗呢個方案。咁呢個方案咧就覺得係誒最完美㗎啦。其實呢個方案出咗嚟。
嗰個new proposal whatsoever，佢都可能係有啲嘢，大家仲想誒on top of嗰個噉嘅proposal咧，再畀一啲誒enhancement嘅噉，所以我就話誒，即係上咗嚟FA panel嗰個報告都未必係一個final嘅咁誒。至於應該要tick幾耐時間咧，噉我我同意。
去睇一睇佢點解咁正確地可以話喺依個條例嘅兩條條例係唔需要更改嘅咧？誒，即係你你有梗係有個legal document喺度啦。噉我想咧就係即係唔係唔信啊，主席啊，但係我去想睇一睇咧。我而家唔係問啊。
喺邊度可以有畀你賦予噉嘅權去咁做？你畀個paper我哋好唔好啊？我一因為因為我唔想叫S.F.C.E.F.C.都係一個獨立，你管佢哋，所以我問政府攞依個文件嚇。未未吧？Answer in English. I think when we did the consultation,誒，we
Obviously, also during the consultation period, and also we know that, for example, Hong Kong U has come out to question the legality and auto virus of the proposal. So all this feedback we will take into account, and we will obviously have to carry out internal examination.
你嗰陣時。
係唔係希望主席政府要畀嘅主席？
多謝曬，多謝政金會嘅緊介。玩呢啲個好玩嘅。
審字嗰度S.F.O.啊嘛，所以佢哋知道係啊，我哋知道好清楚啊嘛，四年啊，大佬即係嗰個標，我好似你而家。
We decided we will have to listen, and this is one of the many many feedback we receive. So we'll obviously take that into consideration. That's all I'm trying to say. Thank you. Thank you, Chairman.
as to how to deal with this issue, so we are not in a position to offer any response to that. We haven't reached a decision as to where to go, but obviously when we eventually present our conclusion and eventually come to FAP panel, we will.
explain the position. I don't. We're not in that position. So I just want to say. But the the the the you just answer that in case of any changes. But we are talking of two different organisation, SFC and the stock exchange. The deputy chairman asked, do you need to change or amend?
Any of the two ordinances that that needs to come back to electorate said that you don't need to change, but now being two organisation in these two organisations that were being governed by the two ordinances, that now you're creating an area a grey area where the people from SFC.
enter into the arena of stock exchange and stock exchange enter into arena with the two levels of committee. what that's why I said that there is no change. well, what right way do you derive that authority to embark on such a scheme? I'm asking not SFC. I'm
demanding the government to give me a paper to identify how the Hong Kong newspaper of ultravirus situation do not arise. But it's up to government to really responsible to the FA panel. Give us a paper on this. Can I just answer now? Ask perhaps maybe.
to to add to it. When I answer the honourable deputy chairman, when he say, do I need to change listing rules? I was just responding to when we present a consultation paper, what we originally envisage. That was our original plan. Because if if we have thought of having to change listing rules.
It would be in the consultation. It wasn't, but since receiving the Hong Kong view, for example, their view, we'll be studying it, and therefore we will then take into account the legal view. We obviously we have to see our own separate view to come to a decision. We're not there, so I'm not saying that we have already.
O.K.，多謝曬。未未啊，Mabel，你想補充？我補充一句啫。誒，嗰個法律嘅誒議題咧，其實喺諮詢文件，佢哋收取嘅嗰個誒啲意見翻嚟咧，係其中一個有提出嚟，大家有提出嘅。咁所以咧，當證監同埋交易所誒草。
好以佢哋日後就住呢個諮詢文件嘅分析同埋個意見嘅進度報告畀立法會呢一個財經事務委員會咧，嗰個法律嘅問題咧，會係喺整個成個個分析裏邊咧，都會係一個重要嘅一環。我哋一定會確保呢一個問題咧，會向誒委員會咧有一個解釋同埋一個交代。多謝主席。
同埋多謝阿石議員。阿石議員，我諗咧，政府希望畀啲答案你啦。個政府係要畀答案，因為政府又要向立法會，因為係立呢條法例嘅去解釋。當佢喺呢個諮詢文件嗰陣時，創造兩個committee出嚟嗰陣時咧，我想問喺現。
有嗰兩條法例之中啊，邊個權畀你去賦予佢呢個權出嚟咁簡單？主席，政府咪話畀我聽啦，佢做咗呢張諮詢文件，佢呢諮詢文件出咗兩個committee出嚟，呢兩個committee喺呢兩條法例下點出嚟嘅咧？我就叫政府畀個批評我啊嘛。OK，希望政府可以答到你。